<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
  <section>
    <p>Copyright (c) 2009-2016 Christoph Ender<br/>All rights reserved.</p>

    <p>Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or without modification, are permitted provided that the following conditions are met:</p>
    <ol>
      <li>Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer.</li>
      <li>Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in the documentation and/or other materials provided with the distribution.</li>
      <li>The name of the author may not be used to endorse or promote products derived from this software without specific prior written permission.</li>
    </ol>

    <p>THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE AUTHOR “AS IS” AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE AUTHOR BE LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA, OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE OF THIS SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <p>This package includes software written by other authors:</p>

    <p>libfizmo includes the Mersenne Twister random number generator, available at <a href="http://www.math.sci.hiroshima-u.ac.jp/~m-mat/MT/MT2002/emt19937ar.html"></a>. This is available via a BSD license, which is stored in the source file “libfizmo/src/interpreter/mt19937ar.c”.</p>

    <p>libfizmo includes hyphenation patterns provided by the hyph-utf8 project at <a href="http://www.ctan.org/tex-archive/language/hyph-utf8/"></a>:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>British english hyphenation patterns as provided by the hyph-utf8 project at <a href="http://www.ctan.org/tex-archive/language/hyph-utf8/"></a> under a permissive license.</li>

      <li>German hyphenation patterns, provided by the hyph-utf8 project at <a href="http://www.ctan.org/tex-archive/language/hyph-utf8/"></a>, distributed under the terms of the LaTeX Project Public License.</li>

      <li>French hyphenation patterns as provided by the hyph-utf8 project at <a href="http://www.ctan.org/tex-archive/language/hyph-utf8/"></a>, distributed under the terms of the MIT License.</li>
    </ul>

    <p>libdrilbo includes code from the pix2gif utility by Mark Howell in ztools, which are available from <a href="http://www.ifarchive.org/indexes/if-archiveXinfocomXtoolsXztools.html"></a>. The copyright status of Mark Howell's work is unknown. Since he released the software for free and since it is also used by multiple other projects it can also be distributed or used freely, to the best of my knowledge.</p>

    <p>libpixelif contains the “Fira Sans” and “Fira Mono” fonts made by Erik Spiekermann and Ralph du Carrois. For information about copyright and licensing see the file <tt>SIL Open Font License.txt</tt> in the following directories:
      <ul>
        <li>libpixelif/fonts/fira-mono</li>
        <li>libpixelif/fonts/fira-sans</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
  </section>
</document>

